Winter, 2007 in Japan,...
2007年冬天
various employment types including the lifelong employment
被認為將永久存續的 終身雇用制
"Economic bubble burst, 1991"
（1991年起，泡沫經濟崩壞）
After a long recession, in an attempt to scale down,
長期的經濟蕭條 使企業必須自行限縮
it became common for companies to seek to outsource.
勞動力外包化加劇
As a result, the number of non-regular employees,
結果造成非正規雇用者
particularly of temp workers, saw explosive growth.
特別是被稱為派遣員工者 爆發性地增加
There are currently three million temp workers in Japan.
現在派遣人口約有三百萬
"Lowest employment rate for college graduates, 2000"
（2000年，應屆畢業生 內定率史上最低）
Temp workers are paid hourly without a bonus
然而薪資是時薪制 也沒有獎金
and with no transportation expenses included.
交通費原則上是自理
Their contract is reviewed every three months.
每三個月就要重新考核契約
It's an unstable and harsh working environment.
其環境嚴苛又不安定
"Temp staffing industry reached four trillion yen, 2005"
（2005年，派遣市場規模 突破四兆圓）
Still, temp workers brave this difficult path.
派遣人員們就在這樣的 荊棘之路堅強地活著
"Andalusia, Spain"
（西班牙，安達魯西亞）
[Foreign language]
（外語）
Haruko?
春子
I hear a strange sound.
有奇怪的聲音
Bring it to me.
幫我拿來
For example, this woman.
譬如說這名女性
Perhaps one day, suddenly, the desk next to you at your company
或許某天你隔壁的辦公桌
will be occupied by a super temp worker like her.
出現像她如此驚人的 超級派遣員工
So it's the next year now.
已經是新年了啊
Haruko?
春子？
I've got to go now.
我該走了
Adios.
再見
"Tokyo"
（東京）
Hello, Mum?
（森美雪，23歲） 喂？媽媽？
"Miyuki Mori, 23, part time worker, income: 810,000 yen"
（打工族，年收入81萬圓）
About the New Years...
我新年沒辦法回去了，抱歉
Don't worry about that.
不用這麼擔心啦
I'll try to make it work in Tokyo a little longer.
我會繼續在東京打拚看看的
There are so many companies out here.
這裡有很多公司啊
I'm sure I'll find a job somewhere.
我一定會找到工作的
Don't worry.
沒問題的
I'll go now.
我要掛囉，先這樣了
Hi there.
辛苦了
"Personal information entry sheet"
（個資登記表）
"Education: Literature degree"
（最高學歷）
Work experience?
工作經驗？
I've got zero.
我沒經驗…
Are you new to this?
-第一次當派遣人員嗎？ -是
We welcome people like you.
我們很歡迎
A temp worker...
所謂的派遣員
signs up to an agency like us...
就是在我們這樣的 派遣公司登記資料
and sent to work at various companies.
然後派遣到各種不同的企業
You'll be paid hourly by our agency.
薪資是時薪制 由我們公司支付
Okay.
-是… -為了登記資料
you'll be tested for common knowledge and PC skills.
會先進行一般常識考 跟確認你的電腦技能
Well...
請問…
Don't worry, it's a very easy test.
沒問題的，非常簡單
Oh sorry, my name is Hitotsugi, the manager.
介紹晚了，我是經理人一木
"Shinya Hitotsugi, 30 Haken Life employee, income:4.02 million yen"
（30歲，派遣生活社員）
Feel free to ask me anything.
有什麼不懂的儘管問我
I don't have high expectations. I just need to find a job quickly.
我的要求不高，只想快點工作
Yes!
嘿咻
"First work day of the year ceremony"
（S&amp;F開工典禮）
Happy New Year.
恭喜
There you go.
嘿咻
Hey.
再來，腰部多用點力啊
Sorry, I'm afraid that I will hit your hand.
很抱歉，我怕搥到部長的手
At this rate, the New Year's will end before we eat pounded rice.
真是的，照你這樣還沒吃到 年糕，新年就要過了
There you go!
好耶
"Takeshi Shoji, S&amp;F employee Income: 625,000 yen"
好耶，阿武，上吧
Director Kirishima.
部長，我要開始了
There.
-部長 -好耶
Yeah!
-什麼事？
I like you.
我喜歡您
Shut up.
少說蠢話了，笨蛋
I'll follow you.
我要追隨您一輩子
Make me your son.
請收我當養子
No thanks.
不要
I'll follow you forever.
我要跟隨您一輩子
Stop talking.
別說了
Director...
部長
"The Sales Division"
（S&amp;F營業部）
Isn't it good?
真好吃呢
I did 80 percent of the work.
這些年糕有八成都是我搗的
Okay, thanks.
-不好意思 -東海林
Satonaka. Follow me.
里中，跟我來
An appointment.
任命書來了
Hey, wait!
等等…
Takeshi Shoji, you're appointed as Chief of Sales Section 2.
我任命東海林武 為販賣二課主任
Thank you.
謝謝您
I'll give it all I have.
我會拚命努力的，部長
Congratulations.
恭喜
Thank you, everyone.
謝謝，謝謝大家
Congratulations, Shoji.
東海林先生，恭喜
Thank you, Ken.
謝謝，小賢
Kensuke Satonaka.
里中賢介
Yes.
是
You're now the chief of Marketing Section.
你負責擔任行銷課主任
Do we have such a section here?
部長，我們有這個課啊？
We decided that it's time for our division to focus on marketing.
雖然起步得晚，但我們部門 也決定在行銷部份投注心力
It's a new team.
是新設的課
Your office will be in the current archives.
辦公室是目前的資料室那裡
I'm counting on you.
我很看好你的，我是認真的
Really.
是真的
Director Kirishima.
部長，那個…
If you emphasise that too much...
越強調這點 反倒有點欲蓋彌彰了
Thank you.
謝謝您
I'll do my best to meet your expectations.
我會照您期望的好好加油
Ken.
小賢…
Marketing Section, huh?
行銷課啊…
I'm sorry, go ahead.
不好意思，請
It's fine, I'm getting off.
我要下車了
Thank you.
不好意思
What?
有事嗎？
Nothing.
沒…
"Word and Excel"
（Word與Excel教學書）
Excuse, do you have any jobs for me yet?
請問… 還沒有工作能介紹給我嗎？
At this rate, I'll lose my apartment.
這樣下去我會被趕出公寓的
We're doing our best.
我也正努力尋找
However, since you have no prior work experience,...
只是像你這樣沒有工作經驗
your options are limited.
能派赴的公司比較有限
Please.
-這點就拜託你了 -抱歉
Please hurry.
快點幫我找到啊
This is Hitotsugi.
喂？我是一木，辛苦了
How is it going?
伊藤小姐，那之後狀況如何？
What?
什麼？
It's over?
受夠了？
Hold on a second.
請等一下
They look down on us temp workers.
那裡的社員都瞧不起派遣人員
They only let us run errands.
只會叫我打雜
They made me go buy their lunch yesterday.
昨天還要我去幫忙買炒麵麵包
That's not good.
那可真糟糕啊
Going to get people's lunches...
你也不是為了幫忙買炒麵麵包 才被派到那裡的嘛
I'll talk to the person in charge.
我馬上跟對方負責人談
Please tell them that I'm quitting.
請幫我跟那間公司說 契約結束了
Ito?
伊藤小姐…伊藤小姐？
Seriously?
饒了我吧
She still has two months left.
契約還有兩個月啊
What about me?
是我的話…
I'd be happy to go buy lunch.
我願意去買炒麵麵包
Director Kirishima.
部長
Another temp worker just quit.
派遣員又突然離職了
The agency is sending a new person.
派遣公司的人 似乎要代接替的人過來
So another interview?
又要面試了啊
Sir, it's a consultation, not an interview.
部長，不能說面試，那叫面談
Oh yeah?
是喔？
A consultation?
面談？
It's different from an interview?
跟面試有什麼不同？
Interviews...
簡而言之 面試在派遣法上是被禁止的
Companies are not supposed to choose temp workers.
我們接受派遣的單位 是不能挑選派遣員的
But they could still turn me down, right?
但也有可能在面談時被刷掉吧
Yes, very possible.
非常有可能
It's basically the same thing.
雖然內容本身一樣
We just cannot call it a job interview.
但不能說是面試，要說是面談
I previously worked in HR.
我之前待在人事部 對這些比較了解
Ask me anything about outsourcing.
派遣的事就交給我吧
Enough with bragging.
別賣弄了
Come with me.
你也一起來
Yes, I'll follow you until the end.
是，我會一輩子追隨部長的
Satonaka.
對了，里中，你也一起來
She's just finished university,
她去年才從大學畢業 技能上還不能說很熟練
But she's a hard worker.
但你會加油的吧
Right?
-森小姐 -是的
Can you use Word?
最起碼會使用Word吧
What? Sure.
什麼？是…
Excel?
那Excel呢？
Yes.
我會
Power Point?
那Power Point呢？
Yes, I can.
會
She can work right away, then.
那就是即戰力了啊
Yes, you can count on me.
是，請包在我身上
By the way, you got Haruko Omae, right?
話說回來，大前春子會來吧
Yes, we've got her. Consultation is with her tomorrow.
是，我已經跟她說好了 明天就會來面談
Okay.
這樣啊
Since Ms Omae will be back,...
只要大前小姐會來
this lady can join us.
另一位就選這位無所謂
We have a new section.
請你去我們新設的行銷課幫忙
Great, I'll do my best.
是，我會加油的
I'm Chief Satonaka.
我是主任，敝姓里中 請多指教
Sir.
部長，那位大前春子是誰啊？
"Marunouchi"
（丸之內）
Sometimes you meet someone,...
跟某些人的邂逅 有時會使自己大幅轉變
Who is that person for me?
對我而言，那個人就是…
Haruko Omae gave a great impact...
大前春子小姐
And...
而且，她也教會了我 非常重要的事物
She taught me that working is living.
「生活即是工作」
"The Pride of The Temp"
派遣員的品格
"A super temp worker makes an appearance"
〝超級派遣員登場〞
Really?
拜託了
Sorry for the wait.
久等了
Some tea?
還泡了茶啊
Great to see you.
-平時受您照顧了 -非常感謝
We proudly present Haruko Omae, a Special A Rank temp worker.
這位就是本公司最引以為傲 特Ａ級的大前春子
So this is her.
就是這位啊
Nice to meet you.
初次見面，我是行銷課的里中
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Sit down.
快坐啊
I'm the Chief of Sales.
我是營業課的主任
But I'm here on behalf of our director.
這次算是臨時部長代理
Since you're a temp, your job is assisting the chief...
畢竟你是派遣員工 會請你支援他跟做些雜事
Where did you work before?
來我們公司之前是做什麼的？
Was my voice too soft?
我聲音太小了嗎？
You heard it, right?
她應該有聽到吧
Where were you before?
來我們公司之前是做什麼的？
Hello?
怪了…
I'm not sure who's the one doing consultation now.
這樣我都搞不清楚 是哪一方在接受面談了
I'll answer for her.
那個…就由我來吧
I'll explain the conditions.
我來說明條件
Conditions?
條件？
The contract is for three months.
契約期間是今天起的三個月
Monday to Friday, 9:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m. with one-hour lunch break.
勤務時間是周一到周五的九點 附中午一小時午休到晚上六點
Extension of contract is not allowed.
契約期絕不接受延長
No work outside of the assigned section.
不做工作範圍之外的事
No work on weekends or overtime.
也不接受假日上班或加班
That's all.
以上
Wait a minute.
等等…
So many "Nos".
不接受什麼的…
Why don't you say anything?
你為何從剛才就一聲不吭的？
Even if you're a temp, we expect you to do overtime if we're busy. Right?
就算是派遣員，真的忙起來 也是要幫忙加班的啊
Sure.
是啊…
It depends on the situation.
這個嘛…就是看情況了
But basically this is how she works.
總之基本上是這樣
That's it.
就是這樣…
Director Kirishima has requested her to start working today.
桐島部長要她今天就開始工作
Is Kirishima serious about hiring her?
部長當真要雇用這個人？
That's crazy.
不太妙吧
She doesn't even blink. Is she alive?
她連眼睛都不眨，還活著嗎？
She moved.
動了
Is this some kind of a joke?
喂，你在開玩笑嗎？
What's with the attitude? Say something.
別在那邊自以為是地喝茶了 倒是說說話啊
This is terrible.
真難喝
You will not regret hiring me.
雇用我絕對不會讓貴公司後悔
I'll work hard for the three months I'm being paid.
我會盡三個月的時薪 該盡的本份
Hourly wage?
時薪該盡的本份？
- Here she comes. - She's the one?
來了來了，那就是特Ａ的
The Special A Rank temp worker.
那就是傳說中的特Ａ級啊？
Hey.
那個…
Marketing Section's here.
行銷課在這裡
Good morning, everyone.
各位早安
Good morning.
早安
I'm Miyuki Mori with Haken Life.
我是從派遣生活來的森美雪
Nice to meet you.
請多指教
I'm also new to this section.
我在這個課也算新人 一起加油吧
Please use this desk.
那麼，森，你就用這個桌子吧
- Okay. - Chief.
-是 -主任
Is this everyone?
這樣就全員到齊了嗎？
Yes. Thank you, Asano.
對，淺野，拜託了
Just me, with one year's experience and the temp workers.
只有進公司一年的我跟派遣員
What a scratch team.
感覺就是湊個數而已
That's not true.
沒這回事
We have an experienced member, Ogasawara.
還有資深的小笠原先生呢
Glad to have you.
拜託了
Thanks.
是
Nice to meet you.
今後請多指教
Marketing Section was recently created.
行銷課還很新
I'm not sure where we should begin myself.
我也還不清楚 要從哪裡開始著手
But let's work together and build a good team.
但我想跟各位攜手合作 打造一個好團隊
Can you give a word, too, Omae?
一句話也好，大前小姐 也來打聲招呼吧
I'll help you out.
我也來幫忙
You don't need to get to work right away.
兩位不用這麼急著工作啊
Get used to the office for today.
今天就先試著習慣職場吧
Omae, you don't need to do anything yet.
大前小姐，你先不用做事 沒關係的
Hey.
喂
Has she been like that?
那個人一直都是那樣？
Yes.
對
Well...
請問…你在生氣嗎？
I'm just following the chief's order to do nothing.
我只是遵守主任要我 先別做事的指示
Problem?
有問題嗎？
Oh, I see.
這樣啊…
Here's your ID.
員工證做好了
You seem to have a lot of free time.
這裡看起來好閒，真羨慕
Can you help me out with this, Temp?
能幫我一下嗎？派遣的
What?
什麼？
What's up with her?
那個人是怎樣啊？
It's her first day.
因為她才第一天來…
Hey.
喂
We're paying you, so work.
拿了時薪就給我好好工作
Not like that, Shoji.
東海林先生，這口氣…
First impression is the key.
一開始最重要了
Or she'll underestimate us.
可別被這套頭毛衣女瞧扁了
Chief, this crazy curly hair is not my boss.
主任 這個捲捲頭不是我的上司
Crazy curly hair?
捲捲頭…
Nobody says that.
最近很少聽人這樣說了
I see.
這樣啊，你完全無視 自己上司以外的人啊
- Yes. - Kidding me?
-對 -想吵架啊？
My name is Haruko Omae.
我叫大前春子
She's useless.
真是派不上用場
Never mind.
算了
Sorry.
-很抱歉，黑岩小姐 -為何是你道歉啊
- Yeah. - Hey.
-就是說啊 -那個…
I'd be happy to do it.
不介意的話讓我去做吧
Oh yeah, we have her.
對呀對呀，還有她嘛
- You're Mori, right? - Yes.
-你姓森是吧 -是
- Good with computers, right? - What?
你電腦很行吧
Yes, I am.
啊…是
This is the revenue by region.
那這是各地區的業績
Compile them by product.
能幫我依商品項目 整理出來嗎？
With sales offices and branches.
把營業所跟分公司都打上去
Sure.
是，明白了
Right away.
我會盡快做好
Take your time, do it roughly.
不用急，大致上做做就好了
Okay.
是
Darn.
真是的
For you, Omae...
那麼就請大前小姐…
Can you make us some tea?
對了，能幫忙泡個茶嗎？
It's noon, so see you later.
12點到了，失陪了
Hey.
喂…
Again.
她剛剛又在看了
She looked at my hair.
那傢伙又瞄了我的頭髮
Watch out for Chief Shoji.
最好對東海林主任防著點
He's good at his job, but he doesn't like temp workers.
他的工作能力是很強
He doesn't hesitate to fire ones he doesn't like.
看不順眼的派遣員工 馬上就會被他踢掉的
Nice.
真不錯
What are you looking at?
你在看哪裡啊？
It appears that...
我們…
they're talking about us.
好像變成被討論的對象了
Enough.
算了吧
Don't get attached to a temp.
要是被派遣員工看上了 可就糟糕囉
This is a secret,
偷偷告訴你
but our director's wife was a temp.
桐島部長的太太 原本也是派遣員
That's rough.
好像滿慘的呢
So was it not her?
是認錯人了嗎…
Wait.
不…那麼強烈的個性 肯定是同一個人
Are you okay, Ken?
小賢，你沒問題吧？
What should I do?
我該怎麼辦才好？
That temp.
那個套頭毛衣女啊
She's the worst of all the ones I've seen.
是我看過的派遣員裡最糟的
But Kirishima wanted her?
真的是桐島部長找她來的嗎？
Yes.
對啊
Maybe she's blackmailing the director.
該不會是被那個套頭毛衣女 抓住什麼小辮子了吧
You guys have a great imagination.
你們還真會妄想啊
Sir...
你們真是的
Don't be stupid. No one can ever blackmail our director.
別說傻話了 部長哪會有什麼小辮子啊
Are you done eating?
部長用餐完了嗎？
I'll clean it for you.
我來幫您收
Sorry.
不好意思，謝謝
Satonaka?
-里中 -是
Do a market research on rice before next Wednesday.
下週三之前，去調查白米市場
Sure.
什麼？
First task for the Marketing Section.
行銷課的第一個工作
You'll present it at the product meeting.
就是在商品開發會議做簡報
Okay.
是
Work hard...
要做出…
and get good results.
成果來喔
Yes, I'll do my best.
是，我會努力的
Thank you.
-謝謝招待 -謝謝
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
Please share the table.
要請兩位併桌了
Hi there.
你好
That looks good.
看起來真好吃呢
Same thing for me, please.
我也要點味噌鯖魚
Brown or white rice?
要糙米飯還是白飯呢
White rice.
白飯
Here you go.
久等了
Excuse me.
我先失陪了
Wait.
等等
Yes?
有什麼事嗎？
- One person. - I'll get this.
這餐由我來請吧
No thanks.
不用了
But...
不不不…
I'm retired and now I work as a part-time worker...
雖然我到了退休年齡後 就變成委託社員了
but I still make enough to buy a temp worker lunch.
但還是請得起派遣員 一頓味噌鯖魚的
No, thank you.
不用費心了
Accept other people's kindness.
就乾脆地接受人家的好意吧
- No, thank you. - You're stubborn.
-不用了 -你還真固執啊
I don't want to sound patronising,
我說這些話不是要賣你人情
but I know that life isn't easy with your low-paying job.
但我知道你這種賺時薪的 很辛苦的
After lunch and transportation, not much would be left.
再加上餐費跟交通費 根本沒剩多少吧
Please don't worry about it.
真的不用您費心了
What are you trying to prove, you poor temp worker?
派遣員那麼窮 到底在逞什麼強啊
We'll present this next Wednesday.
下週三就要做簡報了
We need to research first.
首先是調查的部分…
Where's Omae?
怪了，大前小姐…
That's thoughtful.
真機伶呢
Thanks.
不好意思
You asked me to make tea before lunch.
這是主任您在午休前要我做的
Oh yeah, that's right.
對喔
For me, too? Thank you.
不好意思 還連我的份也泡了…
Is this new tea?
請問…茶葉換了嗎？
No, it's the same tea I found in the kitchen.
沒有，就是平時茶水間的 有問題嗎？
It's very good.
非常好喝
Worth paying 3,000 yen per hour.
這就是時薪三千圓的 泡出來的茶啊
What?
什麼？
Someone from General Affairs told me that she worked for them before.
我在總務那邊聽到的
Her rate is 3,000 yen per hour.
時薪是三千圓
Three thousand yen?
三千圓？
Are you okay?
您沒事吧？小笠原先生
Get a cloth.
快去拿抹布來
It's so hot.
好燙…
Hot.
有夠燙…
"To understand what kind of rice dishes are eaten..."
（米飯料理）
"New products"
（米飯加工市場調查）
Omae?
大前小姐，那個…
It's done.
完成了
What?
什麼？
What's this?
這個…
Look at that.
好厲害
I see my name in it.
還有我的名字呢
What should I do?
我負責做什麼呢？
You'll sort internal references.
你是負責公司內的資料分類
Okay.
是
Ms. Temp?
派遣的
Are you finished?
剛才拜託你的東西做好了嗎？
Sorry, I'm not done yet.
很抱歉，還沒好…
But it's been hours.
你是要做幾小時啊…
What? It's so sloppy.
這也打得太粗略了吧
I can't use this.
根本不能用啊
You mentioned that you can use Excel and Power Point.
你在面談時有說會用 Excel跟Power Point吧
Sorry.
很抱歉…
Sorry? Is that all you can say?
這不是道歉就能了事的吧
Did you lie?
你是騙人的？
No, right?
不會吧？
You didn't, did you?
怎麼會這樣啊
This is unacceptable.
簡直太扯了
That's not a proper way of communicating.
請正確地使用日文
What?
什麼？
Who are you talking to?
你是在對誰說？
Earlier, you told her not to rush and do it roughly.
你剛才說不用急 大致上做做就好了吧
So what?
那又怎樣？
You told her it's okay to take hours and make it sloppy.
這指示不就是要人花好幾小時 做些粗略的東西嗎？
No, I would never be okay with that.
我哪可能下那麼蠢的指示啊
What's with you?
-搞什麼啊 -我要說的就只有這些
Do it all over again.
馬上重做
Okay.
是
Prove that you weren't lying or you'll be in trouble.
無法證明自己沒說謊 你可就不妙囉
Can you help me out, Asano?
淺野，能幫我一下嗎？
Let's take the trash out.
-是 -要倒垃圾了
Oh yeah!
對了，今天要辦個歡迎會
All of us.
大家一起去吧
That sounds good.
真不錯呢
You should come too, Omae.
大前小姐也一起去吧
I'll leave office on time.
下班時間我會準時離開
Please sign this for approval.
請幫忙蓋確認章
What do you think of your team?
大前，那個課怎麼樣？
You might find the members not very capable.
雖然就你看來 或許都是些沒用的社員
You're right.
是啊
What?
啥？
If you need help, I can possibly add more employees.
人手不夠的話
No, thank you. They're useless.
社員都派不上用場，不需要
What?
啥？
If you're hiring,
如果要多派人的話 請找電腦技能好的派遣人員
You don't have rights to decide.
身為派遣員工的你沒這權限吧
All right, I'll consider it.
知道了，我會考慮看看
- Thank you. - What?
謝謝
Sir...
部長
That's unacceptable.
我無法容忍那女人
We use temp workers in order to reduce labour costs.
為了削減人事費才雇用派遣員
That's common sense.
這是企業常識
Just for three months.
就只有三個月而已
You should get rid of her.
已經不需要那女生了吧
She's just not used to the job. It's fine.
森只是還不習慣而已 沒問題的
Maybe Omae can help her out.
只要大前小姐帶著她 很快就會上手了
No way.
不可能啦 那女的哪可能照顧晚輩啊
Why?
怎麼說？
She complained and asked to hire someone who's more skilled.
她還跟部長抱怨 要換個技能更好的派遣人員呢
She did?
大前小姐說的嗎？
So the new temp girl can be replaced.
她想讓新的派遣員來取代她
Manager.
課長，事業部的方針出來了
Azukama, Sekiguchi,
東、關口 今天內整理好品質評價
Takahashi, let's have a meeting when I get back.
高橋，回來之後要開會
Check this.
把總計算出來
Shoji.
東海林先生
You're busy now, right?
你現在很忙吧…
It's okay.
沒關係
You're in my way.
擋路，正式員工
Hey, you temp!
喂，那個派遣的
Pick these up.
至少也該撿起來吧
I can't stand that woman!
不行，我真的很痛恨 那個套頭毛衣女
Look at this.
都捲起來了
My hair is getting all curly!
煩到我頭髮都變捲了
You look fine.
看起來跟平時沒兩樣啊
You think so?
是嗎？
You shouldn't be the one picking them up.
這不該是身為主任的你來撿吧
But thanks.
謝謝
Sorry that I got upset.
我一時失態了，真抱歉
What's going on, Ken?
怎麼了，小賢，有煩惱嗎？
Well...
嗯…
My team doesn't seem to be together, so I was thinking of having...
我們課這樣下去會像一盤散沙 似乎不太好
a welcome dinner.
我想辦個歡迎會
That sounds good.
不錯啊
That's important.
一起喝酒聚餐也是很重要的
Everyone has to be there.
不全員到齊就沒意義了吧
But Omae said she'll leave on time.
但大前小姐說要準時回家
That's the biggest problem that you have now?
你最大的煩惱就是這個啊？
Pull yourself together or she will have everything her way.
身為主任的你不振作點 會被派遣員騎在頭上的
But she is very competent.
不過她工作能力真的很強
Still, she needs to listen to her boss.
但派遣員不聽命令怎麼行啊
All right.
我知道了
I'll make it work.
我會想辦法的
Hi. Thank you for your continuous support.
您好，東海林主任 受您照顧了
Haruko Omae?
大前春子怎麼了？
Satonaka, her boss,
我們公司的里中啊
is at a loss with how to handle her.
被她搞得很煩惱
Hitotsugi,...
一木先生
we may stop taking temp workers from your agency.
我有點不想請貴公司 幫忙找派遣人員了
Wait.
請等一下，這是怎麼回事？
"Questionnaire on rice"
（問卷）
"Please see the attached questionnaire and..."
（實施問卷調查）
The welcome dinner is tonight.
今天要辦歡迎會吧
I've been looking forward to this.
對我來說這是唯一的樂趣了
Where will we go?
要去哪間店呢？
About that...
關於這個
- Omae... - It's fine.
-因為大前小姐… -沒問題
I spoke with Hitotsugi.
我已經跟一木先生施壓了
You love work dinners, don't you?
小笠原先生最愛喝酒了
Don't drink too much.
可別喝太多囉
Got it.
是
Leave it to me.
等著瞧吧
I'll leaving now.
我先走了
See you tomorrow.
辛苦了
Marketing Section.
是，這裡是行銷課
Omae?
大前小姐
It's Hitotsugi.
是一木先生打來的
What did you mean?
施壓是？
- Just wait and see. - What is it?
-等著看吧 -什麼？
You guys will have fun tonight.
好戲要上場了
I understand, Hitotsugi.
我明白你的意思了，一木先生
If I have to go to this dinner and pour drinks for people,...
與其要我出席不想去的歡迎會 強迫我去喝酒
I'd rather be fired.
開除我也無所謂
Please end my contract right now.
現在就中止契約
Please tell that to Director Kirishima. Bye.
請幫我轉達給桐島部長
No way.
不會吧…
Omae.
大前
I'm so sorry...
真抱歉
for my stupid employees.
我的員工真是太蠢了
Those idiots...
那些蠢蛋 不去聚個餐就沒勁工作
I'll make an exception and pay extra three hours for overtime.
我會特別付你三小時的加班費
So please join them.
能請你陪陪他們嗎？
Overtime?
加班費？
Why, for a temp?
為何要為了一個派遣的 做到這樣啊
Shut up!
少囉嗦
Okay.
是
As I mentioned first, I don't do overtime.
正如面談時所說的，我不加班
"Tokyo STB Trust Bank"
（東京STB信託銀行）
"Tokyo Central Trust Bank"
（東京中央信託銀行）
"Tokyo Central Trust Bunk Declares Bankruptcy"
（負債7985億圓）
I don't know too much about Haruko Omae.
我也不太了解大前春子小姐
She has many high-level certifications.
只知道她有很多高階證照
She works for three months and disappears for three months.
工作三個月後就會消失三個月
She's exceptionally competent.
不過她的時薪跟技能層級 完全不同
Don't feel bad.
你不用因此感到自卑
Please don't quit. Okay?
總之請千萬別辭職
Not before the contract ends.
中途解除契約是最傷腦筋的
What if they fire me?
如果是對方要我離職呢？
That's even worse.
那就更傷腦筋了
"Cafe Cantante"
（歌手咖啡廳）
I'm back.
-我回來了 -歡迎回來
Welcome back, Haru.
小春，歡迎回來
I'll be here again for three months.
我又要來打擾三個月了
Only three months again?
這次也只做三個月嗎？
Yes, I'll leave once my contract ends.
沒錯，契約一到就拜拜
Help yourself to this.
不嫌棄的話請吃吧
Haruko.
春子
A song?
要不要來個一首？
Okay.
這樣啊
"Bushido"
（武士道）
"Dangerous substance exam"
（甲級危險物證照題庫）
"Pasco Flamenco"
（佛朗明哥舞）
Who's this?
誰？
Hello?
喂？
This is Miyuki Mori.
我是森美雪
Sorry to bother you on your day off.
抱歉在假日打擾你
Hitotsugi gave me your number.
我是從一木先生那邊 問到電話號碼的
Omae?
那個…大前小姐…
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
I...
我…在面談時
I told them a lie.
撒了謊…
I'm sure everyone is aware of that by now.
我想大家應該早就看穿了吧
So what?
有問題嗎？
I'm truly sorry.
真的很抱歉
I'll try my best in the future,
今後我會拚命努力的
so please don't get me fired.
請不要讓我離職
That's up to them to decide.
決定權在正式員工上 跟我這個派遣員無關
I...
我只能依靠大前小姐你了
Please delete my number right away and never call me again.
這是個資，請把我的號碼刪掉 別再打來了
You wanted to see me?
你找我嗎？
This.
這裡面錯誤一堆
I've had our temp worker redo everything.
我請我這邊的派遣員 全都重做過了
Here.
拿去
I'm sorry.
真的很抱歉
I mentioned this to Director Kirishima.
我也跟部長報告過了
Here you go.
-部長，麻煩了 -好
Omae?
大前小姐，也請協助森吧
We only have two days till our presentation.
距離簡報只剩兩天了
We still have two days.
要加緊腳步了
You don't want to help her?
這是不想幫忙的意思嗎？
It's fine, I'll work faster.
沒關係的，我會加快速度
She says it's fine.
她本人是這麼說的
Never mind.
算了…
She makes all the temp workers look bad.
派遣就是這樣才讓人詬病
That's right.
對啊
Sorry.
-很抱歉 -不，不是說小森你啦
I'm really fine. I'll do my best.
真的沒關係，我會加油的
See you later.
辛苦了
Mori, right?
她叫森是吧
I was in the consultation with her.
那女孩是我面談的
She's got a lot of problems.
但似乎有些問題啊
If you don't think you can help her out,
連你也放棄她的話 大概就只能請她走人了
You're asking a temp worker to help out another temp.
這是想讓派遣來照顧派遣
Don't you find that a problem?
社員本身就沒問題嗎？
You and your opinions.
你也真敢說呢
Bye.
-先走了，辛苦了 -辛苦了
There's no way I'll finish in time.
完全趕不上
Oh yeah.
對了
- He looks exactly like Shoji. - Really?
-跟東海林先生超像的 -真的假的？
- Mori? - Yes?
-怪了，小森 -是
You're still here.
你還在啊？
I just finished.
我剛做完
Okay.
-這樣啊 -對
- Nice work. - Thank you.
-辛苦了
See you later.
辛苦了
See you tomorrow.
那我先離開了
Wait.
怪了
"User error"
（用戶錯誤）
What?
什麼？
This doesn't make any sense.
真是的，真是莫名其妙
"User error"
（用戶錯誤）
What should I do?
怎麼辦…
Seventy-five days left.
還有75天啊…
Can someone please help me?
真是的…誰來幫幫我啊…
Wow, it's so late.
天啊，已經這時間了
What should I do?
怎麼辦…
To S and F in Marunouchi. Please hurry.
不好意思，請載我到丸之內的 S&amp;F，幫我趕一下
Here is fine.
這邊停就行了
I made it. I'm so relieved.
太好了，趕上了
Here you go.
一、二、三…來
Hi there, Ms. Temp.
哎呀，派遣的
You took a taxi?
搭計程車來上班啊？
Kuroiwa.
黑岩小姐…
Thank you.
謝謝
Good morning.
早安
Your hair is all messy.
頭髮還真亂呢
Where did you come from?
是從哪裡來的呢？
I overslept.
不，我睡過頭了
I was running late.
差點遲到
You've got bed head.
頭髮都亂翹了
Omae...
大前小姐，那個…
Do you by any chance have a hair product?
你應該沒有順髮水 之類的東西吧
No, I don't.
沒有
How much can you do before tomorrow?
到明天簡報前 還可以做幾套出來？
Oh no.
怎麼辦…
What is it?
森，怎麼了？
The reference material I input for the presentation...
那個…為了簡報 打的資料…在計程車…
You left it?
你忘在車上了？
I often do that, too.
我也常會這樣
Did you get a receipt?
你有拿收據嗎？
Which company?
記得是哪間計程車公司嗎？
Which taxi company?
計程車…那個…
I'm not sure.
那個…我不知道…
Calm down, Mori.
森，冷靜一下
It's for tomorrow morning.
明天早上才要開會
You can re-enter everything.
只要趕快重新打就趕得上了
Where's the disk?
資料光碟呢？
Well...
那個…那個也…
It was in the paper bag that I left in the taxi.
一起放在紙袋，丟在車上了
What?
什麼？
I...
那個…
I'm truly sorry.
真的很抱歉，那個…
I'll go look for it now.
我馬上去找
Hey, wait.
等等…
I'll check taxi companies.
我逐一去問計程車公司吧
Yes, do that.
拜託了
Sorry.
不好意思，那個…
Has anybody turned in a red paper bag?
請問有人撿到一個 紅色紙袋嗎？
She took it to Marunouchi.
是在九點左右搭到丸之內的車
I don't remember.
沒有耶
Next one.
去下一間問吧
Why did you let a temp worker take home
為何讓派遣員 把那麼重要的資料帶回家啊
I didn't know about it.
雖然我不知情 但一樣是我的責任
This is a huge deal.
這可不是寫反省書就行了啊
It's something a temp did.
這是派遣人員擅自作主 就讓派遣公司來負責
I'll deal with the damage claim.
我會跟對方要求損害賠償的
That's right.
就是說啊，肯定要開除了
But it's more serious than that.
但那女孩根本也負不起這責任
It was my lack of supervision.
不…是我督導不周
What are you still doing?
都什麼時刻了 你還在做什麼？
I'm working. Problem?
我在工作，有問題嗎？
Remember?
瞧
She has to leave office on time today as always.
這個人今天也要準時回家呢
What's up with you?
你在想什麼啊
Omae.
大前小姐
What should we do?
這種情況下該怎麼辦才好？
I have nothing to do with this.
跟我無關
- What? - Hey.
你說什麼？
What makes you a Special A Rank?
你到底哪裡是 特Ａ級的派遣員了？
You're not good at all.
你根本不是什麼優秀的派遣員
You might be good with computers but you have no social skills.
就算打電腦的速度再快 待人處事的能力也是零
Bad attitude, no manners,
自大又沒禮貌
no team work, not adapting.
不合群又不配合職場
When there's someone like you, it lowers everyone's motivation.
光是有一個你這樣的人 連我都沒勁了
If you're not happy with my attitude,
對我的工作態度不滿 請去跟經理人一木講
Saying stuff like that is not acting properly!
你這種地方根本毫無人性
Do you even...
你們…
consider a temp a person?
有把派遣員當人看嗎？
Don't answer with questions.
不准用問題回答我的問題
As a temp worker, you just do whatever an employee tells you.
派遣人員只要 乖乖聽正式員工的話就好了
That's not right.
東海林先生，這樣說不對啦
I'm panicking.
我也慌了
I don't know what to do.
不知道該怎麼辦才好
Omae.
大前小姐，拜託了
Please help us.
請助我一臂之力吧
What?
咦？
Where are you going?
你要去哪裡？
She went for lunch because it's noon.
已經12點了，是要去吃飯吧
See, Ken,...
看到了嗎？小賢
she only thinks about lunch even in a time like this.
那個套頭毛衣女
She's no good.
根本是派遣員之中的人渣
Hello?
喂？
Did you find it?
淺野，找到了
Well...
關於這個…
we managed to find the taxi company,
總算查到計程車公司了
but the taxi was scrapped.
但那輛車報廢了
Scrapped?
-報廢？ -小森下車之後
The driver is in the hospital.
司機被送去醫院了
And the disk?
光碟呢？
It was sent to the scrapyard with the car.
好像跟車子
Excuse me. Is anybody here?
不好意思，有人在嗎？
Anybody here?
有人在嗎？
Satonaka.
里中先生
I'm truly sorry.
真的很抱歉
There's still hope if it's not scrapped yet.
只要還沒真的被報廢的話 就有希望的
Silver car.
銀色的…
I found it.
找到了
I found it. It's that one.
找到了，就是那輛
The presentation...
簡報…
is first thing tomorrow morning, right?
是明天一早吧？
Hey!
喂喂…
Mori.
小森…
Are you okay?
你沒事吧？
- You want to die? - Are you all right?
-小森，你想死啊？ -沒事吧？
Look at you.
真是的
Here.
沒事吧？
Omae?
大前小姐？
Get out of my way.
快讓開
Omae.
-大前小姐… -快去旁邊吧
Here it is.
有了
I found it.
找到了
It's here, Omae.
找到了，大前小姐
Where are you going, Omae?
大前小姐，你要去哪裡？
I'm going for lunch.
吃午餐
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
Hi.
那個…
I'm very sorry...
給你添了這麼多麻煩
for all the trouble I caused.
真的很抱歉
I'm just dragging everyone down,...
我只會扯大家的後腿
so I'll quit.
我會辭職
Thank you for all you did for me while I was there.
雖然時間很短，但受你照顧了
What can I get you?
要點什麼？
Since it's my last day, can I join you?
這是最後了 能跟你一起吃嗎？
I got rejected by 23 companies.
就職考那時 我考了23間都落榜了
So for eight months after I graduated from college,...
然後大學畢業後八個月以來
I had several part-time jobs.
就一直到處打工
My parents in Gunma told me to come home,...
群馬的爸媽要我回去
but I thought there would still be a chance for me in Tokyo.
但我想只要待在東京 應該還會有機會
When I visited this company,
在面談時去到那間公司時
working in a nice company like that seemed great.
我想自己要是能在 這麼氣派的地方工作就好了
I got a bit too excited.
一時被沖昏了頭
That's why I told them a lie.
忍不住就說謊了
But some people are just no good no matter what they do.
但是沒用的人 果然做什麼也沒用
If I could work at a company like that,...
要是我能在那樣的公司工作
my life would've been different.
人生肯定早就不一樣了
That's a big mistake.
這可就大錯特錯了
You could still get laid off...
就算當上正式員工 也有可能被裁員
and they could go out of business.
而且公司倒閉就完了
Like the Titanic that sank.
就像鐵達尼號沉沒一樣
Sorry?
什麼？
Still, people give everything they have to the company.
明明是這樣卻每天為了公司 斡旋、拍馬屁、爭出頭
Is that...
那個，我…
Waste of time.
沒用的
All of that.
都是白費功夫
Even with a 100-year recession
就算繼續不景氣一百年
or an economic crisis, I'll still survive.
全日本的公司都倒閉了 我也不會有事
A temp should trust...
派遣員只需要相信…
only themselves and money.
自己跟時薪
With techniques and skills to survive,...
只要有活下去的技術跟技能
you can live however you want.
就能隨心所欲地過活
Are you by any chance trying to cheer me up?
難道…你是在鼓勵我嗎？
- Excuse me. - Yes.
-不好意思 -是
Tea, please.
請給我茶
In any case,...
總之
thank you for coming to my rescue earlier.
剛才很謝謝你幫我
I didn't come to your rescue.
我沒幫你
It's part of my job.
那是工作的一環
Besides, you're not safe.
而且你也沒得救
You'll be fired.
你會被開除，今天就會被開除
You should never take work home.
本來就不該把工作帶回家
- Sorry. - Apologising to me does nothing.
-很抱歉 -別跟我道歉，開除就是開除
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
For the rest of the day, work hard for your hourly wage.
還有半天
That's what I'd do.
如果是我就會這麼做
Thank you.
謝謝光臨
Chief.
主任
Please give me another chance.
請再讓我做一次吧
Since we have the disk back, I'll not report this to my boss.
光碟也找回來了 這件事我不會跟上面說
As a penalty,...
作為懲罰，要請你無薪加班了
Okay.
是
Good luck.
加油
You looked quite impressive today.
不過你今天也很厲害呢
I had no idea you had a crane licence.
居然有怪手的執照 真令人驚訝呢
I didn't know, either.
就是說啊
So what?
有問題嗎？
So you'll keep the temp?
結果不開除那個派遣嗎？
You're so easy on them.
你太天真了啦，小賢
You're right.
是啊
When we first joined the company,...
我們還是菜鳥時
the older lady told us how to answer phone calls...
從接電話開始教我們的 業務部的阿姨
and Chief Kawasaki often treated us to dinner.
還有每次加班都會請我們 吃關東煮的川崎主任
Remember that?
你還記得嗎？
Yeah.
記得
I wonder how they are now.
不知道大家都怎麼樣了
Everyone got laid off.
大家都被裁員了
Now it's just temp workers who are strangers to us.
接下來只會有 越來越多毫不相關的派遣員
Can you accept that?
你能接受嗎？
For me,...
我啊
I wanted to keep working with them.
想永遠跟那些人一些工作
We shared meals together,...
吃同一鍋飯
we cried and laughed,...
流淚歡笑
like a family.
像家人一樣
I thought we'd be together forever.
原本可以永遠這樣下去的
It doesn't make sense.
真讓人難以接受
It's like the space invaders game.
這樣根本就像 太空侵略者一樣啊
Shoji.
東海林先生
That makes you sound old.
你的比喻也太老派了吧
Don't get shot down, okay?
你啊，可別被擊落囉
Omae.
大前小姐
- Good morning. - Morning.
-早安
Morning.
早安
With Mori's help, we managed to finish.
森也很努力，總算完成了
We stayed until 11:00 p.m. last night.
昨天跟大家一起做到11點呢
How is it possible to spend that many hours on that?
那麼點工作怎麼會做到11點？
I'll follow you forever, Omae.
我要一輩子追隨大前小姐
Good tea.
這茶真好喝呢
We the Marketing Section...
營業部行銷課
did our own market research on processed rice products.
從販賣部門的觀點出發
We did a food service industry research on restaurants...
調查以餐廳為對象的外食跟…
Nice work.
辛苦了
I was so nervous.
我好緊張
You did a good job.
做得很好啊
Satonaka.
里中
Yes.
是
Good job for your first task.
以第一次來說做得很好了
Thank you.
謝謝
I'll take you to somewhere nice tonight.
今晚帶你們去個好地方
This way.
這裡這裡
Over here.
真是的
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
I thought we were going to a club.
還以為要帶我們上夜店
But flamenco? Really?
結果居然是來看佛朗明哥舞
Ever been to a place like this?
東海林先生 有來過這種地方嗎？
- No. - Hey.
-才沒有呢 -快來這裡坐
I've always wanted to see flamenco.
我早就想看看佛朗明哥舞了
Thank you.
謝謝部長
Flamenco isn't for watching but for listening.
佛朗明哥舞不是用看的 是用聽的
You know a lot about it.
您真內行呢
She makes fun of us instead of making us look good.
那個人就是喜歡看 正式員工出糗
What's the pride of a temp?
派遣員的自尊是什麼？
That's a stupid question.
那是什麼無聊的問題？
It's a stapler battle.
請跟我用釘書機對決
What's more important than pride?
比尊嚴更重要的是什麼？
"This drama series is a fiction"
（本劇純屬虛構）